בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody.
Today's דף daf is דף יח. daf yud chet. We're in the
middle of some really classic אגדתא. Aggadata. It's in the context of
two very important themes that are being intertwined here. It sort of
came because we spoke about not building stadia and scaffolds and platforms
in terms of doing for the Romans as places of their courts
and of their justice because or their judgment because obviously there was
cases particularly in the context of the Hadrianic persecutions but otherwise as
well in which Jews were persecuted and prosecuted and were sort of
executed by the Romans either for trumped up charges or for real
charges but for unfair laws and so on. And it was sort
of assisting them in those types of violent acts that actually would
you know cause the whatever led you know caused the execution of
many Jews and of great Rabbis. So as a result we sort
of start with one such story to remind you of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer who was charged with heresy and this was you know
and then we had a whole discussion about that about his engagement
with maybe some Jewish Christians and so on and he actually got
out of it. And that and then the גמרא Gemara that led
the גמרא Gemara to have a very important sort of digression which
has been like a major theme that I've been telling you all
along which is like what are the real threats nowadays? The real
threats nowadays are not עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. The גמרא Gemara says
that explicitly. The real threats nowadays are like heresies sort of like
things that are intellectually seductive but maybe pernicious in terms of our
commitment to our beliefs and so on. And then there's רשות Rashus
the government things positions of power that could you know sort of
pull us away from you know in terms of the larger world
and זנות Zenus and sort of sexual freedom. So the גמרא Gemara
really then sort of spent its time like developing those themes and
we had the famous story about רבי אלעזר בן דורדיא, Rabbi Elazar
ben Durdaya, was it רבי אלעזר? Rabbi Elazar? רבי אלעזר בן דורדיא.
Rabbi Elazar ben Durdaya.
Anyway that you know about who who when he tried to leave
his life of
promiscuousness and running after prostitutes or whatever he he died as a
result. It was so difficult. You know so anyway so that's important
in terms of the general theme of what are sort of the
things that are seducing us away from a life of like keeping
on the straight and narrow and the path of תורה. Torah. And
then that actually then ties back, I don't think I mentioned this
yesterday, because then we get back to other cases where the Roman
government you know persecuted and you know and executed great Rabbis etc.
the הרוגי מלכות. Harugei Malchus. And the story about where they were
where they took רבי אליעזר בן פרטיא Rabbi Eliezer ben Pratya and
רבי חנניה בן תרדיון. Rabbi Hananya ben Teradyon.
So רבי אליעזר בן פרטא Rabbi Eliezer ben Prata actually got out
of all the charges that were leveled against him and now we're
about to get to the story of רבי חנינא בן תרדיון. Rabbi
Hanina ben Teradyon. But certainly what רבי חנינא, Rabbi Hanina, excuse me,
רבי חנינא בן תרדיון Rabbi Hanina ben Teradyon and
and but of course the charges here that are leveled against him
is primarily that they're keeping מצוות Mitzvos and teaching תורה Torah when
the you know in the context of the Hadrianic persecutions when the
government is trying to outlaw it. So again it's also does I
should say you know fit into that larger theme that what's out
there in the larger world that's seducing us, power and intellectual seduction
and sexual freedom, and our what sort of keeps us anchored is
a life of commitment to like you know תורה, Torah, תורה ומצוות.
Torah u'Mitzvos. And it was exactly that commitment to תורה ומצוות Torah
u'Mitzvos that the sort of Romans were trying to you know stamp
out and that at that period and that you know that was
why these great Rabbis martyred themselves. Okay.
So most of the time the Roman Empire, I mustn't say it
was benign, but it was quiet. Right. But there were intense periods
of intense persecution.
Yes. Thank you. That is correct. Specifically in the context of these
Hadrianic persecutions. It was not like it was ongoing. There were there
were periods. I think you said that extremely well of intense persecution
and like the rest of the time it was like oh it's
a lot of you know they they build the roads and they
have the bathhouses and it's great to be part of the Roman
you know of the Roman Empire as long
as you're not getting persecuted.
Exactly. As long as as long as we're not being persecuted. Okay.
So anyway, alright. So now we get to the story about רבי
חנינא בן תרדיון. Rabbi Hanina ben Teradyon. Okay. So let's take a
look. And he only did the גמרא Gemara says remind you that
the גמרא Gemara said that you know he only was charged with
one thing. But he in the end we already know the end
at the beginning. He in the end is going to be found
guilty. And the reason the גמרא Gemara said that he's going to
be found guilty or that רבי אליעזר בן פרטא Rabbi Eliezer ben
Prata told him he was going to be found guilty was because
you know he was not, or was it the
גמרא, Gemara, no no no, it says תניא, Tanya, שנתפסו, she-nitpasu, עסקת
בתורה וגמילות חסדים, askata baTorah u'gemilus chasadim, ואני לא... v'ani lo...
No he himself, excuse me, he himself said to רבי אליעזר בן
פרטא Rabbi Eliezer ben Prata I know I will be found... because
I only involved myself in תורה Torah and not in תורה וגמילות
חסדים. Torah u-bgmilus chasadim. Right, so that's also very important, right, about
that sort of a life not just of learning תורה Torah but
a life of deeds and he himself acknowledged that he was too
focused solely on תורה Torah and he sort of sees that that
is ultimately, you know, why he is going to be found guilty,
so keep that in mind, you know, it's is it like this
to one degree it's like this divine punishment, you didn't involve yourself
enough in good deeds, you only involved yourself, so that's not why
you're going to be, excuse me I shouldn't say it that way,
that's not why you're going to be put to death, but that's
why you're not going to be saved, because you don't have enough
merit because you focused only on תורה, Torah, but there also will
be, as we're about to see, a very practical tie-in. Because he
only focused on תורה Torah ultimately that's what got him into trouble
with the Romans. It was sort of like before by, you know,
by Rabbi Eliezer because he was like, you know, involved himself with
discussion with the with the Jewish Christians that was why he felt
like he was punished and by God, you know, and that but
that's also why the Romans seized him and suspected him of heresy.
Okay, so it's like both like it's why God is doing it
and it's why the Romans are doing it.
Okay, is there another גמרא Gemara I recall that the reason why
he didn't get out of it was because like he was like
too like unbending.
Okay we're about to get—that's the גמרא Gemara we're about to get
to.
Okay also the Rebbe is always saying like תורה Torah will lead
to good deeds it's not—in this case it didn't actually happen.
Right well some people focus only on תורה Torah exactly. Alright so
the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב', Yud Zayin Amud Beis, three lines
from the bottom. So אתיוהו לרבי חנינא בן תרדיון as'yu l'Rabbi Chanina
ben Teradyon so we already know the end right he says I
know I'm going to get—I'm going to get executed—I'm going to—and it's
because I only focused on תורה. Torah. So they brought Rabbi Chanina
ben Teradyon. אמרו ליה amru leh so the Romans said to him
אמאי קעסקת באורייתא amai kaasakt b'Oraisa why did you involve yourself with
תורה? Torah? Now the מהרש"א Maharsha points out that this is different
to what they said to Rabbi Eliezer ben Prata. To Rabbi Eliezer
ben Prata they said—what
they said—תנית tanita which is the word of like Rabbinic literature okay
and somehow that's I don't know that suggests itself more in some
type of like a private context. עסקת באורייתא asakt b'Oraisa like—and we're
going to see the whole idea of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
you involved yourself in תורה Torah and there's going to be this
much more sense of this public teaching of תורה. Torah.
Okay you see the Romans for the most part weren't anti-Jew it
was political. Some individual Roman senators and writers were right but for—but
it was a political.
Yeah yeah that is correct. Okay אמר להו amar lehu he said
to them כאשר צוני ה' אלקי kaasher tzivani Hashem Elokai I am
doing like the Lord my God teaches me so like he sort
of like threw it in their face again this evokes what we
taught yesterday compared to Rabbi Eliezer where they said to Rabbi Eliezer
was very smart he both sort of spoke about God but he
did it in a subtle way that they were thinking that he
was talking about them. He said נאמן עלי הדיין ne'eman alai hadayan
right this Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon is like the same way the
teaching of תורה Torah was more public his response here you know
is—you know he's just very like in your face I'm going to
publicly do it without any—without any consideration of the consequences. Okay so
it's not very he's not very like sort of subtle or you
know figuring out you know and not just diplomatic right he's not
very he's not being very practical smart in a practical way here.
Okay מיד גזרו עליו לשריפה miyad gazru alav l'sreifah okay that's it
a חוצפה chutzpah so you're going to—we're going to burn you ועל
אשתו להריגה v'al ishto l'harigah we'll execute your wife ועל בתו לשבת
בקובה של זונה v'al bito lasheves b'kubah shel zonah your whole family
is now going to get you know is now going to—to be
punished and your daughter will—put her in the—will put her amongst the
prostitutes right maybe the state prostitutes I don't know what.
We mean we know the theology behind him he said I didn't
do
enough גמילות חסדים gmilus chasadim right. Alright let's keep on reading alright
Michael just a little patient okay everything you said so far. Okay
so עליו לשריפה שהיה הוגה את השם באותיותיו alav l'sreifah shehayah hogeh
es hashem b'osiyosav
now the גמרא Gemara wants to understand why did he get this
punishment okay now because yesterday we sort of said that since he
only involved himself in תורה Torah nothing else he wasn't saved but
saying you're not saved doesn't explain why you're punished why was he
being punished what did he do wrong so he would articulate God's
name you know exactly as it's spelled he wouldn't say אדון Adon
when he said the יוד-קא-ואו-קא Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei he said it explicitly the way
it was written. Okay now רש"י Rashi says it means he used
like the 48-letter name of God which has these all these like
super powers but תוספות Tosafos just says he just explicitly said God's
name I think תוספות's Tosafos's explanation is also fits better in the
larger theme of what's going on here. So והיכי עביד הכי. v'heichi
avid hachi.
What did תוספות Tosafos say?
He just said God's name explicitly יוד-קא-ואו-קא. Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei. והיכי עביד הכי v'heichi
avid hachi how did he do that meaning okay it's one thing
to say he was punished but he wouldn't have transgressed something that
was clearly violated right. והתנן ואלו שאין להם חלק לעולם הבא האומר
אין תורה מן השמים אין תחיית המתים מן התורה אבא שאול אומר
אף ההוגה את השם באותיותיו veha tenan v'elu she'ein lahem chelek l'olam
haba omer ein torah min hashamayim ein techiyas hameisim min hatorah Abba
Shaul omer af hahogeh es hashem b'osiyosav even somebody for who is—who
says God's name the way it's spelled and presumably we assuming that
we go like אבא שאול Abba Shaul so the גמרא Gemara said
no להתלמד עבד l'hislamed avad he just did it in order to
like you know he wasn't doing it for you know maybe purposes
of using its power or he wasn't doing it The משנה Mishnah
said ואין תחיית המתים מן התורה, v'ein techiyas ha-meisim min ha-torah, אבא
שאול Abba Shaul says אף ההוגה את השם באותיותיו, af ha-hogeh es
ha-shem b'osiyosav, even somebody who also says God's name the way it's
spelled, and presuming we, assuming that we go like אבא שאול, Abba
Shaul, so the גמרא Gemara said no, ללמד עביד. lelamed avid. He
just did it in order to like, you know, he wasn't doing
it for, you know, maybe purposes of using its power or he
wasn't doing it promiscuously. He was doing it, you know, in order
to study, in order to understand, like, you know, to understand תורה.
Torah. And again, this is very much consistent. Well, we'll see then,
why did he punish like, figure up your mind, either he either
why did he violate or why was he punished? So we'll get
there. But but the ques- but the point here is is that
he's doing it for the sake of like of study, of under-
you know, it's pu- all about תורה Torah study, okay? So I
mean not that this is whatever. Anyway בשלמא bishlama of it. כדתניא
kid'tanya לא תלמד לעשות lo silmad la'asos אבל אתה למד להבין ולהורות.
aval atah lomed l'havin u'l'horos. You can't learn about how the non-Jew-
the, you know, the non-Jews
worship their gods, but in order- if because you you're interested in
that you might want to do it, okay? But if you want
to just understand it like for תורה Torah purposes, it's allowed. So
somehow we make an analogy that since that's true over there about
the studying of other religions, it's true here about saying God's name
explicitly. So then the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי טעמא איענש? ela
mai ta'ama i-anash? So okay, if it was allowed, why was he
punished? משום דהוגה את השם בפרהסיא דהוה mishum d'hogeh es ha-shem b'farhesya
d'havah
because he did it in public. And this is of course, you
know, foreshadowing exactly what the problem's going to be. And exactly what
we've already seen the problem is, like a little subtlety please. Like
you know, do it more private, do your teaching of תורה Torah
in private, do your saying of God's name in private. For him
it's like everything is out there. I believe in this, I don't
want to have to work to accommodate the Romans in any way,
not in terms of my practice and teaching תורה, Torah, you know,
not in terms of or whatever, not in terms of how I
respond to them when they're prose- when they're- what- you know, when
they're about to, you know, you know, prosecute me. I'm not going
to try to accommodate myself at all. Okay, so if I'm going
to learn- learn God's name באותיותיו, b'osiyosav, I'm not going to care
about the consequences that other people might be overhearing or whatever, it's
I'm just totally focused on my learning of תורה. Torah. What? Yeah.
Not necessarily intentionally provocative, but completely uncon- uncaring about the about about
you know, the
consequences of doing it, you know, in a non-accommodating way.
If he was under the Soviets, if you learned in the basement
no one cared, but if you went up there in public.
There you go, that's a good analogy. Okay, ועל אשתו להריגה, v'al
ishto l'harigah, now why did his wife get executed? דלא מיחייא d'lo
michaya because she could have maybe stopped him, okay, and she didn't
protest. מכאן אמרו, mikan amru, this is this is- what are you
talking about? That's what we should be very sensitive to nowadays. The
whole idea of what's it called about the passive enabler. All you
know, whatever, not that he was evil, but what's the line? All
evil men need to- to succeed is for good men to stand
by and do nothing, something like that.
Okay, isn't it because she- she lost her חלק לעולם הבא, chelek
l'olam ha-ba, you know, because she enabled his sin, so therefore she
got killed?
I mean, that doesn't- No no no, it's not- he doesn't- it's
not the problem of חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam ha-ba. חלק לעולם
הבא chelek l'olam ha-ba he had, because he was- because he was
doing it לשמה. lishmah. The doing it בפרהסיא, b'farhesya, the problem was
was that it was not proper respect for God- for God's name.
It wasn't the act of הוגה את השם באותיותיו, hogeh es ha-shem
b'osiyosav, it was the act בפרהסיא. b'farhesya. Okay, דלא מיחייא. d'lo michaya.
She didn't protest, she didn't stop him. מכאן אמרו כל מי שיש
בידו למחות ואינו מוחה נענש עליו. mikan amru kol mi sheyesh b'yado
limchos v'eino mocheh ne'enash alav. Anybody who has in his ability to
stop- your a passive enabler and you don't stop, you are punished
with that person. And all those- the implication is almost as if
you were a- the actual perpetrator yourself and not just an enabler.
Not the exact same death penalty.
Just like in law, if you've anything to do with the conspiracy,
if you drive the- No no no, that's different. That you're an
active member of a- of a- of a plan. This is just
you're a passive enabler. Okay, but anyway, but a passive enabler you
actually get almost the same punishment. I mean, they both get killed,
just her not as- as horrifically as him. ועל בתו לישב בקובה
של זונות. v'al bito leishev b'kubbah shel zonos. What? Can you apply
this to our responsibility to- to act in
terms
of the political- Of course. Well you mean, you know, in all
cases, right? If you think injustice is being done or whatever, what
does it mean to be a passive enabler? You know, that's like
very much also in terms of this whole like Me Too. How
many people, you know, knew about stuff and didn't do anything? Right,
I mean going back to Harvey Weinstein and in general, know things
are going on and just are, you know, being passive enablers. So
that allows evil to flourish, okay?
And most people in the Holocaust weren't collaborators.
Exactly, exactly. Most people in the Holocaust were exactly, bystanders. Exactly, exactly.
Okay, exactly, harsh.
Yep,
and- he did it- לשמה lishmah בפרהסיא? b'farhesya? What were you saying
in the beginning?
Yeah, ועל בתו לישב בקובה של זונות. v'al bito leishev b'kubbah shel
zonos. Now why did his daughter deserve to get punished to become
a prostitute, to be put in the- in the- whatever, in that-
the house of prostitution? אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, פעם אחת
היתה בתו מהלכת לפני גדולי רומי. pa'am achas haysa bito mehaleches lifnei
gedolei Romi.
Once she had to be- happened to be walking in front of
some great, you know, Roman personages. ואמרו, v'amru, and they looked at
her and they said, "Oh, כמה נאות פסיעותיה של ריבא זו." kamah
na'os p'siyoseiha shel riva zu. Look how- look how beautiful her footsteps
are. Oh, you know, the- which is actually, you know, like- like
they're paying attention to her, but it's not like she's act- you
know, she's being provocative or whatever. She's not act- you know, dressing
in a- in an immodest way or- and you know, talk about
dress. Anyway, she's not acting in a provocative type of a way,
but they took notice of her. Okay? ומיד דקדקה בפסיעותיה. u'miyad dikdekah
b'p'siyoseiha. Oh, you know, people like when- when people pay attention to
them. So she started being very careful about how she walked, even
more careful so that people would, you know, would- you know, would
like notice it. So- What? So- Yeah, והיינו דאמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, Ve'hainu de'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, מאי דכתיב עוני עקבי יסובני,
Mai de'chtiv avoni akeivai yesubeni, the sin of my footsteps or of
my heels wrap around me, עונות שאדם דש בעקביו, Avonot she'adam dash
be'akeivav, בעולם הזה, ba'olam hazeh, sins that people,
things that people treat as trivial this world. They just trample on
it like with their heels. It's like it's not even recognized as
weighty because you're so sort of disregarding of them, so מסובין לו
ליום הדין. mesubin lo leyom hadin. They will wrap around you for
the day of judgment. Okay, so anyway, but obviously that was a
play of the word about footsteps. Okay, but anyway, but the point
being, there's like some מידה כנגד מידה middah kineged middah here. She
wanted people to pay attention to her. She didn't even go out
with that
intention, but once she saw people were paying attention, she wanted a
little bit more attention, and it was obviously connected to some sense
of male attention and whatever. So as a result now she's going
to be turned into a prostitute. Seems pretty darn harsh if you
ask me. Okay. So,
okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says בשעה שיצאו שלשתן. Beshah sheyatzeu
shloshtan. Oh, this seems very harsh, right? How terrible is her getting
the שריפה? sreifah? Okay, as far as yesterday, I
understand, right? She was just walking and she wanted a few people,
oh, all of a sudden she got a little flattered and wanted
a few people to pay a little more attention to her for
that few minutes, whatever. Anyway, okay. בשעה שיצאו שלשתן, Beshah sheyatzeu shloshtan,
by the way though, notice the point that the גמרא Gemara made
before, like what were sort of
the, actually, I'll pause on that for a minute. Okay. בשעה שיצאו
שלשתן, Beshah sheyatzeu shloshtan, when the three of them went out, צדקו
עליהם את הדין, tzidku aleihem et hadin, and they were to be
executed, he or her to be put in this place of prostitute,
צדקו עליהם
את הדין. tzidku aleihem et hadin. They sort of said that God's
justice was just, the צידוק הדין, tziduk hadin, this thing of צידוק
הדין, tziduk hadin, which is what you say at the time like
of a funeral and when you're taking
which basically recognizes that you accept the justice of God's judgment, even
though things sometimes don't make sense and as we see right now,
it seems completely disproportionate to what the sin was, this profound righteous
act
of, how do they translate it in English? I'm missing the right
word. For what? צידוק הדין. tziduk hadin. Justice? Righteousness of the judgment.
The righteousness of the judgment, there's a better word for that. Justice?
I know, there's a better technical word for צידוק הדין. tziduk hadin.
Whatever. Anyway, we're going to go on.
Okay, so anyway, accepting the justice of God's judgment.
Fine, all right. That's not the word I was looking for. Yes.
Okay, צדקו עליהם את הדין. tzidku aleihem et hadin. Okay, הוא אמר,
Hu amar, he said, הצור תמים פעלו, Hatzur tamim po'alo, the rock,
right, perfect is His ways. ואשתו אמרה, Ve'ishto amrah, אל אמונה ואין
עול, El emunah ve'ein avel, which is the end of the same
פסוק. pasuk. The,
a God of trustworthiness or faith, there is no perversion. בתו אמרה,
Bito amrah, גדול העצה ורב העליליה אשר עיניך פקוחות על כל דרכי
איש להגיד לאיש כפעלו, Gadol ha'eitza verav ha'aliliyah asher einecha pekuchoat al
kol darchei ish le'agid le'ish kefe'alo, I forget the exact end of
the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, great is the understanding that Your eyes are
open on all the paths of people to give everybody what is
his due. The real punchline is the end of it, that You,
God, give everyone what is their due. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, said
Rabbi, כמה גדולים צדיקים הללו שנתזמנו להן שלשה מקראות של צידוק הדין
בשעת צידוק הדין. Kama gedolim tzaddikim hallalu shenizdamnu lahen shlosha mikra'ot shel
tziduk hadin besha'at tziduk hadin. So the word צדיק tzaddik here is
completely repeated. How great are these righteous people that the verses that
are the verses for the צידוק הדין, tziduk hadin, presumably the meaning
that we use nowadays because they've become in our liturgy of צידוק
הדין, tziduk hadin, it occurred to them at the time when the
justice was being done, they exactly somehow knew the right פסוקים pesukim
that they should be saying. Because normally you say the צידוק הדין,
tziduk hadin, right?
Or a person says before he's likely to die.
Right, that's true too. That's a very good point. Thank you for
mentioning that. Right, normally you say the, that's a good point, if
I was going to say normally you say the צידוק הדין, tziduk
hadin, like the mourners say it after a death. Here they're saying
it about themselves when they are about to die, and it was
just pointed out actually, somebody when they, if they're doing a וידוי
viduy on their deathbed, that also, what? Yeah. Do the same.
Right, that also is the time, the וידוי viduy is the confession,
to do the
צידוק הדין, tziduk hadin, which is sort of accepting the death that's
impending. All right, so anyway, but it's interesting, because here they're obviously,
we're still calling them צדיקים tzaddikim even though we're saying they did
a sin that was worthy of being punished. So somehow we're sort
of holding both realities, that they could be these totally righteous people,
which we assume they are, and it seems like a completely disproportionate
reason that they're being, getting this horrific punishment, and they're just still
doing the צידוק הדין. tziduk hadin. And that's part of what makes
them צדיקים. tzaddikim. And yes, somehow we also have to do the
צידוק הדין tziduk hadin and somehow accept God's judgment. Okay, so, all
right, so now it says, okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We talked
yesterday. Now we're going to go a little backwards. Now we already
know the end, סוף מעשה במחשבה תחילה. Sof ma'aseh bemachshavah techilah. Now
we already know the end of the story, now we're going to
zoom backwards to find what a previous story that predicts this end.
Okay, so we're almost going to tell the same story in a
different way. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, כשחלה רבי יוסי בן קיסמא.
Keshechalah Rabbi Yossi ben Kisma. No, when Rabbi Yossi ben Kisma fell
ill, הלך רבי חנינא בן תרדיון לבקרו. Halach Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon
levakro. Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon, who now we know what his end
is going to be, went to visit him. אמר לו, Amar lo,
so he said to him, there he was Rabbi Yossi ben Kisma.
כשחלה רבי יוסי בן קיסמא או רבי יוסי בן חסמא K'she-chala Rabbi
Yose ben Kisma o Rabbi Yose ben Chisma fell ill, הלך רבי
חנינא בן תרדיון לבקרו. halach Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon l'vakro. Rabbi Chanina
ben Teradyon who now we know what his end is going to
be went to visit him. אמר לו, Amar lo, so he said
to him there he there was Rabbi Yose ben Kisma on his
deathbed and he said to this Chanina who came to visit him,
חנינא אחי, Chanina achi, Chanina my brother, אי אתה יודע שאומה זו
מן השמים
המליכוה? i ata yodeia she-uma zu min ha-shamayim himlichua? How, what are
you doing? You're publicly defying the Romans. Don't you understand that they
have been given
reign, power, dominion by God? It's clear that that's the way the
world is working and that this is all somehow part of God's
plan. שהחריבה את ביתו, she-hechriva et beito, meaning it's not just that
they're powerful but God is trying to stop it. It's clear that
this is part of God's plan. שהחריבה את ביתו, she-hechriva et beito,
if God, if they destroyed the בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash, God would
not have allowed them to do that if this was not part
of God's plan. ושרפה את היכלו והרגה את חסידיו. ve-sarfa et heichalo
ve-harga et chasidav. Look at how much power they've had over us.
They've already murdered great righteous people amongst the Jews. ואיבדה את טובו
ve-avda et tuvo and they've destroyed the goodness of God. טובו, tuvo,
I'm sorry,
טובו, tuvo, right, God's good people of God's nation. ועדיין היא קיימת
ve-adayin hi kayamat and it's still exists, so clearly whatever, again, just
like צידוק הדין, tziduk ha-din, we can't understand it, but clearly this
is the way God, they have power. God wants them to have
power right now.
Roman Empire was the longest in Israel.
There you go. ואני שמעתי עליך שאתה יושב ועוסק בתורה ומקהיל קהילות
ברבים. ve-ani shamati alecha she-ata yoshev ve-oseik ba-Torah u-makhil kehillot ba-rabbim.
I have heard that you are sitting and learning Torah, gathering, remember
what they said to him, אמאי עסקת באורייתא? amai asakta ba-oraita? It's
exactly these words. עוסק בתורה, oseik ba-Torah, but עוסק oseik in this
public way, gathering the masses in public. וספר תורה מונח לך בחיקך
ve-sefer Torah munach lecha be-cheikecha and you're there publicly, symbolically even doing
it. You're not just teaching words and then they come by and
they say what are you doing and you say we're learning
geometry. You're being very, you're symbolically, you got the ספר תורה sefer
Torah right there in your chest. ואמר לו, ve-amar lo, he said
back to him, מן השמים ירחמו. min ha-shamayim yerachamu. From heaven they
will have mercy. אמר לו, amar lo, this is such a great
line. So Rabbi Yose ben Kisma
said back to him, אני אומר לך דברים של טעם ואתה אומר
לי מן השמים ירחמו? ani omer lecha devarim shel ta'am ve-ata omer
li min ha-shamayim yerachamu? I'm talking to you about a rational argument,
I'm making a powerful point, I'm giving you good advice and you
say the ריבונו של עולם Ribbono shel Olam will help. Like you
are being so living in some other world and you are just
bringing to trouble upon yourself, disaster upon yourself. Okay, so that's way
exactly Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon, right, he did not want to accommodate.
He just unrealistically expected God to have compassion or he didn't care
about that. He was just going to do what he was going
to do.
And we see this other times, it seems to me that other
rabbis get these great...
You might get a נס nes if you, who got the נס
nes yesterday? The person who was smart and the person who wasn't
doing it in public. No, so no, the point is that you
can't be irresponsible. Yeah, there are stories that sometimes rabbis are saved
with miracles. But I don't think you'll find that many of those
stories have the rabbis acting completely irresponsibly and bringing upon themselves this
trouble. Exactly. All right, you know what, guys? We're not having private
discussions. וספר תורה מונח לך בחיקך. ve-sefer Torah munach lecha be-cheikecha. ואמר
לו, ve-amar lo,
he said back to him, ואמר לו, ve-amar lo, oh we already
did that. תמה אני אם לא ישרפו אותך ואת ספר תורה באש.
tamay ani im lo yisrefu otcha ve-et sefer Torah ba-esh. I am
astounded
if you and your ספר תורה sefer Torah will not be destroyed.
Now I also want to remind you that ספר תורה מונח לך
בחיקך sefer Torah munach lecha be-cheikecha was the first opening מדרש midrash
of this מסכת masechet where God comes to עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba
and the ספר תורה sefer Torah is מונח בחיקו munach be-cheiko and
God and whoever is עוסק בזה oseik ba-zeh וייטול שכרו. ve-yitol secharo.
So here he's doing the same. He's got the ספר תורה, sefer
Torah, he's being עוסק oseik etc. You could say, oh, he's acting
like God, right? It's very sort of interesting the themes here. Like
on the one hand, the whole theme is that keeping Torah keeps
you on the straight and narrow is exactly what you gotta do
to protect yourself from the religious dangers of this world. But in
the future, it'll be very public. God will have the ספר תורה
sefer Torah בחיקו. be-cheiko. Right now it might not make so much
sense to do it in sort of this like public way and
to think that the future is already here and to trust in
God, like we also have to find ways to how to accommodate
ourselves to the realities. Which is a lot of what this מסכת
masechet is. How do you live amongst the pagans or whatever and
accommodate yourself to those realities? So he's sort of living in עולם
הבא Olam Ha-Ba type of a life. He's already got the ספר
תורה מונח בחיקו. sefer Torah munach be-cheiko. He's not at all accommodating.
Okay, so yes, the ספר תורה sefer Torah is central, but it
doesn't mean you go about it this way. Okay. So, okay. תמה
אני אם לא
ישרפו אותך ואת ספר תורה באש. tamay ani im lo yisrefu otcha
ve-et sefer Torah ba-esh. אמר לו רבי מה אני לחיי עולם הבא?
amar lo Rabbi ma ani le-chayei Olam Ha-Ba? Will I get עולם
הבא? Olam Ha-Ba? Which is a very fascinating type of a question.
Like, why did he think he wouldn't and why did he have
to ask him? So remember at the previous עמוד amud when he
was going out to be executed, he said, oh, I'm going to
be found guilty because I was only עוסק בתורה oseik ba-Torah as
opposed to you, Rabbi Elazar ben Perata, you were עוסק בתורה ובגמילות
חסדים. oseik ba-Torah u-v'gemilut chasadim. So he understood in himself that he
wasn't doing all that he was supposed to be doing. The גמרא
Gemara even said it was like לא אלוהי אמת. lo elohei emet.
Like he wasn't even fully living a life of implementing Torah in
a practical way. So the same way his Torah wasn't always translated
practically into גמילות חסדים, gemilut chasadim, his whole עוסק בתורה oseik ba-Torah
was not very practical. is not very recognizing the practical world. And
maybe to some degree he even recognized that maybe he's not, I
mean it's funny to think he didn't think he would get עולם
הבא. olam haba. I mean that echoes the עולם הבא olam haba
before that whole thing. But maybe he said like, look, I gotta
do where, I gotta do what I gotta do. Like this is
just, it's sort of like what's his name who sort of said
בן
עזאי, Ben Azzai, who said like, you know, I just gotta learn
תורה, Torah, I can't get married. Like, you know, it's like this
is where my passion is, this is what I've gotta do, like
I can't worry about this other stuff. I can't worry about building
an empire, I can't worry about doing גמילות חסדים. gmilut chasadim. Okay,
maybe he recognized that there are consequences so he even was wondering
if he was going to get עולם הבא. olam haba. מני לחיי
עולם הבא. mani l'chayei olam haba. אמר לו
כלום מעשה בא לידך? amar lo klum ma'aseh ba l'yadcha? And here's
the point about not just like the תורה Torah but the מעשה.
ma'aseh. Was there some act of like good deed, an act, not
learning תורה? Torah? Why wouldn't he say what do you mean מעשה
בא לידך? ma'aseh ba l'yadcha? I've been spending the last 10 years
teaching תורה Torah in public in defiance of the Roman order. No,
that's not going to get you עולם הבא, olam haba, buddy, right?
You know, it's like so funny. So oh, it's like did you
do some מעשה? ma'aseh? כלום מעשה בא לידך? klum ma'aseh ba l'yadcha?
So אמר לו, amar lo, and there's a story
that we say, I mean, I don't know actually, is it... אמר
לו, amar lo, no, whatever
Michael, these statements are not totally consistent. אמר לו, amar lo, he's
teaching its point. אמר לו מעות של פורים נתחלפו לי במעות של
צדקה. amar lo ma'ot shel Purim nitchalfu li b'ma'ot shel tzedakah. Yes,
at one time I accidentally mixed up some פורים Purim money with
צדקה tzedakah money וחלקתים לעניים v'chilaktim l'aniyyim and nevertheless I whatever, whatever
the specifics are, I drew on my own funds to give the
פורים Purim money to the עניים. aniyyim. אמר לו אם כן מחלקך
יהיה חלקי ומגורלך יהיה גורלי, amar lo im ken mechalkecha yihiyeh chelki
umigoralcha yihiyeh gorali, if so, with your portion will be my portion
and from your lot will be my, you know, whatever, same way
of saying it, my portion will be with, my lot will be
with yours. Okay, אמרו לא היו ימים מועטים עד שנפטר רבי יוסי
בן קיסמא, amru lo hayu yamim mu'atim ad sheniftar Rabbi Yosei ben
Kisma, רבי יוסי בן קיסמא Rabbi Yosei ben Kisma passed away והלכו
כל גדולי רומי לקברו v'halchu kol gedolei Romi l'kivro and all the
greats of Rome went to bury him, meaning this was a guy
who knew how to work with the, you know, with the government
in power. Like they recognized his greatness and here, you know, and
they even went for his
burial. והספידוהו הספד גדול v'hispiduhu hesped gadol and they even
eulogized him. Alright? ובחזרתן, u'vachazartan, now when they came back מצאו לרבי
חנינא בן תרדיון, matzu l'Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon, they found רבי חנינא
בן תרדיון Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon שהיה יושב ועוסק בתורה. shehayah yoshev
v'osek baTorah. He was just going on his way. So here it
was, in some way he knew that you know his actions were
not smart, he even made him suspect whether he would get עולם
הבא. olam haba. Okay? And he just was keep on doing it.
Okay? שהיה... shehayah... the person he trusted to tell him whether he
would get עולם הבא, olam haba, you know, he didn't trust enough
to listen to his advice. Alright? It's very strange. Okay, not strange,
it tells you about his personality. ועוסק ומקהיל קהילות ברבים וספר תורה
מונח לו בחיקו. v'osek u'makhil kehillot b'rabbim v'sefer Torah munach lo b'cheiko.
Of course, he also points out that always strikes me is, you
know what? He was there teaching תורה Torah in the masses when
the גדולי רומי gedolei Romi were coming back from the funeral, which
means he wasn't where? He didn't go to the funeral of this
great Rabbi that he... anyway, so he was just so much, you
know, single-minded. Okay? והביאוהו
וכרכוהו בספר תורה, v'hevi'uhu v'karchuhu b'sefer Torah, so they took him and
they said, oh, you're off about the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, you're
so identified with the תורה Torah that you can't separate yourself from
it? So here now we have the whole idea of sort of,
you know, making him one with the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. They
wrapped the ספר תורה sefer Torah around him because that's his whole
point. He's like, he's cleaving to the ספר תורה sefer Torah like
he can't, you know, he can't, nothing he can do to loosen
the grip. So they wrapped him in the ספר תורה sefer Torah
והקיפוהו בחבילי זמורות, v'hikifuhu b'chavilei zmorot, they also they then they surrounded
him with, you know, these wood, you know, sticks והציתו בהן את
האור v'hitzitu bahen et ha'or and they lit the fire. והביאו ספוגין
של צמר, v'hevi'u sfogin shel tzemar, the famous, once they brought, you
know, the these sponges of wool ושראום במים והניחום על לבו, v'shara'um
b'mayim v'henichum al libo, they immersed them in water and they put
them on his heart כדי שלא תצא נשמתו מהרה, kedei shelo tetzei
nishmato meherah, so it'd be a very painful death, he should die
a slow death. אמרה לו בתו, amrah lo bito, his daughter said
to him, אבא אראך בכך? Abba ere'acha b'kach? Father, this is how
I have to see you? This is like, you know, to such,
you know, to be, you know, to be in such anguish and
to be in such a disgrace? אמר לה, amar lah, so אמר
לה amar lah he said to her, אלמלא אני נשרפתי לבדי היה
דבר קשה לי, ilmalei ani nisrafti l'vadi hayah davar kasheh li, had
I just been burned alone, that would be difficult for me because
I would be, have been ripped away from the תורה. Torah. עכשיו
שאני נשרף וספר תורה עמי, achshav she'ani nisraf v'sefer Torah immi, now
that I'm being burned with the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, like it's
all about him, I mean the powerful image, right? You cannot separate
him. He is one with the תורה, Torah, right? He can't accommodate
to the real world. He's living in another world and he's one
with the תורה. Torah. So now that I'm being burnt with the
תורה Torah and I'm totally identifying with the תורה Torah even in
my death, מי שמבקש עלבונה של ספר תורה, mi shemivakesh elbonah shel
sefer Torah, the one, God, who is going to come to defend
the offense against the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, הוא יבקש עלבוני, hu
yivakesh elboni, he will come to defend, you know, my, you know,
my suffering and the offense against me. I have lived my life
as one with the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, so God will come,
you know, again, he's not even at his moment of death, right?
Willing to acknowledge like, ah, maybe he should have acted otherwise. Right?
Which is the point. Like, you know, like he's sort of like,
I am happy to die for this. You know? So I'm happy
to die for the fact that I completely made myself one with
the ספר תורה sefer Torah and I believe that God will come,
you know, ultimately, you know, not to save me but... In this
world, but ultimately, you know, to reward you.
It's the extraordinary value of making your values
align with that of the Torah. It's not a value though, that's
the point. Okay, okay, אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru lo talmidav, his תלמידים
talmidim said to him, רבי מה אתה רואה? Rebbi, mah atah ro'eh?
What do you see? אמר להם, Amar lahen, גליונין נשרפין, gilyonin nisrafin,
I see the meaning, the as like the and others say, they
sensed something unusual was happening, you know, or maybe they just assumed
that he would have had some vision, but they sensed something unusual
was happening. So what are you seeing? So he says, I see
a גליונין נשרפין gilyonin nisrafin or גוילים נשרפין, gvilin nisrafin, I see
that the parchment is being burnt ואותיות פורחות, ve'otiyot porchot, and the
and the letters are flying up to heaven. And obviously the point
being, him too, his body is being destroyed and the soul going
up to heaven, and he is sort of, the whole point about,
he is one with the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. אף אתה פתח
פיך ותכנס בך אש, Af atah ptach picha vetikanes becha esh, so
they said to him, open up your mouth and let the fire
go into you. אמר להם, Amar lahen, מוטב שיטלנה מי שנתנה ואל
יחבל הוא בעצמו. Mutav sheyitlenah mi shenatanah ve'al yechabel hu be'atzmo.
Better the one who gave the soul should give it, and a
person should not do self-injury, injure oneself. This is of course very
important when it comes to sort of this, this, there's very little
in the גמרא Gemara that can be used for the for this
entire field of Jewish medical ethics about, you know, withdrawing treatment and
so on, because the גמרא Gemara doesn't really deal with it anyway.
So there's like three little scraps of גמרא Gemara that people use
to develop a whole field of medical ethics, and this is one
of them. Okay, which is like, you know, obviously right. Anyway, you
know, but do not obviously, certainly about what do you call it,
about euthanasia or whatever, you know, do not do any injury to
yourself, you just have to let the soul depart, you cannot do
anything to speed up that
process. אמר לו קלצטונירי, Amar lo Kaltztoniri, so a certain קלצטונירי, Kaltztoniri,
I don't know whatever that word is, but it's obviously some Roman
officer. How do they translate it?
One responsible for punishments.
Okay, a Roman officer responsible for punishments. רבי אם אני מרבה בשלהבת
ונוטל ספוגין של צמר מעל לבך, Rebbi, im ani marbeh bashalhevet venotel
sfugin shel tze'mer me'al libcha, if I help you out, I make
the flame high and I take off the sponges, אתה מביאני לחיי
העולם הבא? Atah mevi'ani lechayei ha'olam haba? Will you bring me to
the world to come? אמר לו הן, Amar lo hen, yes. השבע
לי, Hashava li, swear to me. נשבע לו, Nishba lo, he swore
to him. מיד הרבה בשלהבת ונטל ספוגים של צמר מעל
לבו יצאה נשמתו במהרה. Miyad hirbah bashalhevet venatal sfugim shel tze'mer me'al
libo yatz'ah nishmato bimherah. Okay, and then he died quickly. Of course
the irony here being two things. Number one is I'm not going
to injure myself, but this non-Jew, sure, let him go ahead and
participate in bringing about my death. I don't know, non-Jews are also
prohibited to commit murder, right? So there's like a very interesting double
standard going on here. And the other point being that he's now,
he now not only can predict who's going to get עולם הבא,
olam haba, he can actually determine who's going to get עולם הבא,
olam haba, promise it to this person, swear to him, but he
himself wasn't certain about his own עולם הבא. olam haba. Yeah, so
it's like very bizarre, you
know.
Anyway, maybe he's also gained clarity at moment of death.
Maybe. אף הוא קפץ ונפל
לתוך האור. Af hu kafatz venafal letoch ha'or.
Even this Roman officer jumped into the fire to kill himself because
obviously he knew he was going to get in trouble presumably with
the Romans for what he had done. יצתה בת קול ואמרה, Yatzata
bat kol ve'amrah, a heavenly voice came out and said, רבי חנניה
בן תרדיון וקלצטונירי מזומנים הם לחיי העולם הבא. Rebbi Chananya ben Teradyon
veKaltztoniri mezumanim hem lechayei ha'olam haba. רבי חנניה בן תרדיון Rebbi Chananya
ben Teradyon and this Roman officer are both going to get עולם
הבא. olam haba. Okay, remember that was exactly the story before about
רבי אלעזר בן דורדיא, Rebbi Elazar ben Durdaya, who was it? רבי
אלעזר בן דורדיא, Rebbi Elazar ben Durdaya, right, דורדיא, Durdaya, whoever it
was. Okay, they're both going to get עולם הבא. olam haba. בכה
רבי ואמר יש קונה עולמו בשעה אחת ויש קונה עולמו בכמה שנים.
Bacha Rebbi ve'amar yesh koneh olamo besha'ah achat veyesh koneh olamo bekama
shanim. One achieves his reward in one moment, this קלצטונירי, Kaltztoniri, what?
Year too. Yeah, yeah, it was the exact same line from before.
Okay, and so over many years. You know, but the other interesting
thing that in for in my mind is, right, is that like
the גמרא Gemara here is obviously quite critical about רבי חנניה בן
תרדיון. Rebbi Chananya ben Teradyon. You know, he suffered this death, he
gets עולם הבא, olam haba, but you know, he himself was uncertain
about his עולם הבא. olam haba. The גמרא Gemara even said like,
you know, he wasn't saved because he didn't do the מעשים טובים,
ma'asim tovim, the whole thing. So, so the question I get is
that by identifying, you know, Rebbi says oh, some people get it
in one moment, some people take their whole lives. You know, but
still at some level you assume that people that they devote their
whole lives and get עולם הבא olam haba by devoting their whole
lives get a different type of עולם הבא olam haba than the
person who gets it in one minute. But here, the fact that
the בת קול bat kol came out and said both of their
names at once, you know, Rebbi, you know, this great rabbi and
this Roman nobody who just did one good act, they're both going
to get עולם הבא, olam haba, it almost like equates them. Right?
So it, you know, it raises again the question about like how,
you know, makes us a little bit feel like, you know, that,
that, it sort of echoes the sense that he himself was uncertain
about his עולם הבא. olam haba. Like, you know, don't go ahead
and think that just because he is, I mean he's a martyr,
of course, you know, whatever, nobody is questioning his greatness, but don't
think that he did the right thing, you know, he, or what
he did was, you know, obviously it's was not the right way
to sort of navigate this situation. It would be much harder to
get עולם הזה olam hazeh than עולם הבא. olam haba. That's a
good point too, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara shows like
this. Now when the story is not over. ברוריה, Bruriah, ברוריה, Bruriah,
דביתהו דרבי מאיר, deveitehu deRebbi Meir, Rebbi Meir's wife. A lot of
famous stories about ברוריה, Bruriah, but maybe you didn't know this part
about her. ברתיה דרבי חנניה בן תרדיון, Berateih deRebbi Chananya ben Teradyon,
she was Rebbi Chananya ben Teradyon's daughter. Okay, now of course it
says his daughter was
assigned to this
place of
prostitution,
that was presumably his unmarried
daughter. Since ברוריה Bruriah was
married to
part of Rebbi Meir's household, she was- She escaped this fate. Okay,
but הוי *Havai* she was, אמרה ליה *amra leh*, she said to
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, זיל במילתא דיתבא אחותי בקובה של זונות *zil
be milta d'yatba achasai bekuba shel zonos*. It's a disgrace to me
that my sister is there in this house of, in this shed,
or whatever it is, a hut of prostitution. Of course, it's funny
she didn't say, I'm concerned for my sister that she's been assigned
that life. Okay, שקל תרקבא דדינרי *shakal tarkava d'dinari*, so רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* took a whole like bag full of דינרי dinari *dinari*.
ואזל ואמר *va'azal ve'amar*, and he went and he said, אי ברורא
עבדת באיסורא *ei brura avdas be'issura*,
if she has not been violated, ליעביד ניסא *lya'avid nisa*, miracle will
be done and she'll be saved. ואי עבדת איסורא *ve'ei avdas issura*,
if she has been violated, meaning לא ליעביד לה ניסא *lo lya'avid
lah nisa*, so miracle but yeah, but he's not doing it in
a public, right, he's being smart. The point is, be smart. Okay,
don't be stupid. Be smart. Okay, ליעביד לה ניסא *lya'avid nisa*, a
miracle will be done. So anyway, but of course what's also deeply
disturbing here is that whether a Roman violated her determines whether or
not she should deserve being saved? Like that's not something you can,
well it's gonna seem in the story maybe she could control it
a little bit, but how do you control it? The Romans are
basically assigning you to a life of prostitution. So it's again, it's
this whole big problem that when something happens to a woman, by
a man, it becomes somehow the woman's fault. The woman becomes defiled
and you know, and then the woman somehow suffers as a result.
Do you think he means to say if she didn't do it
willingly? Well, we'll see what it says.
Right, it says איתעביד בה *itavid bah*, done to her. Okay, so
let's take a look. Maybe. אזל נקש נפשיה כחד פרשא *azal nakash
nafshiah k'chad parsha*, he went up and he dressed up like a
certain like of a soldier, a knight. אמר amar, לה השמיעני לי
*amar lah hashmi'ini li*, so he went to the house of prostitution
and he said like, come, I'm gonna hire you. Listen to me,
come and have sex with me. אמרה ליה *amra leh*, she said
to him, דשטנא אנא *dishtana ana*, no I can't. I'm having my
period, I'm a נדה *niddah*. Not the halachic point of a נדה
*niddah*, but basically like people presumably wouldn't want to have sex with
them. אמר לה *amar lah*, מיתרחנא מרתח *mitrachna mirtach*, I'll wait for
you. Okay, I'll come back in a few days. אמרה ליה *amra
leh*, נפישן טובא דשפירן מינאי *nefishan tuva d'shapiran minai*, why what do
you want me? There's a lot of women here that are much
more beautiful than I am. אמר *amar*, so he said רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* said, שמע מינה לא עבדת איסורא *shma mina lo avdas
issura*, I see that no that she has not had sex with
any any man. כל דאתי אמר לה הכי *kol d'ati amar lah
hachi*, it must be that anytime somebody tries to hire her, she
dissuades him this way. Of course, the point is, doesn't mean she's
always successful, right? And especially since she's being forced into this life
of prostitution. But anyway, but he chose to read it and maybe
if we want to say that this is what it meant before,
that he chose to understand that it meant that she never had
that she didn't have sex. Or certainly that she didn't willingly go
along with it. אזל לגבי שומרא דידה *azal legabei shomra didah*, he
went to her, the guy who was watching over her. אמר ליה
הבה ניהלי *amar leh hava nihali*, give her to me. Meaning, I'll
buy her off of you. So אמר ליה *amar leh*, he said
to him, מיסתפינא ממלכותא *mistafina mimalchusa*, I'm afraid from the government. I
have to keep her, these זונות *zonos* in line.
And so אמר ליה *amar leh*, שקול תרקבא דדינרא *shakol tarkava d'dinra*,
take this whole bag full of דינרא *dinra*. פלגא פלח *palga plach*,
half of them use as an offering, like as it says, to
bribe the Roman officers that'll get you in trouble. ופלגא ליהוי לך
*u'palga le'hava lach*, and the other half keep for yourself. אמר ליה
וכי שלמי מאי עבידנא *amar leh ve'chi shalmi mai avidna*, what do
I do after the bribe money is used up and they're still
asking for more bribes? Now the מהרש"א *Maharsha* has an interesting insight.
The מהרש"א *Maharsha* says that maybe it's not just a bribe. Maybe
the point was, the reason that they assigned her to a house
of prostitution, do you remember the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before? Right, this
is echoing the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before, right, that the Romans, they
make these, their houses of prostitution and they speak about the Romans
collecting a מכס *machas*, collecting a tax. So the מהרש"א *Maharsha* said
that maybe what they meant was that they actually get a tax,
they get a cut of the, like in some countries, where is
it that the prostitution is legalized? In Amsterdam or whatever, other countries,
what's Vegas? Right, Vegas, that's true. But anyway, but
the government actually profits from it because then they have to report
their earnings or whatever.
Anyway, it was part of the idolatrous rite, the prostitution in the
temple.
Right, although I don't know if that was זונה *zona*. That was
more like קדשה *kedesha* or something. קדשה *kedesha*. Whatever, anyway, but yeah,
I'm not sure this is the same. Anyway, the מהרש"א *Maharsha* reads
it
that part of the reason that they did this was it was
like state-run prostitution and they got a percentage of it. So then
he's saying, so I can give the what she should have been
earning, I can give them out of this bag of דינרא *dinra*,
but eventually it's gonna run out and they're gonna want her earnings.
So what do I do? וכי שלמי מאי עבידנא *ve'chi shalmi mai
avidna*? אמר ליה אימא אלהא דמאיר ענני elaha deMeir aneni, *amar leh
eima elaha de'Meir aneni*, say the God of Meir save me, ומישזבת
*u'mishtazvas*, and you'll be saved. And he thinks okay and ומישזבת *u'mishtazvas*.
No, no, I'm sorry, and you'll be saved. Though he didn't trust
it. אמר ליה *amar leh*, ומי יימר דהכי איכא *u'mi yemar d'hachi
ika*? Who's gonna say that that's gonna actually do any good? אמר
ליה השתא חזית *amar leh hashta chazis*, I'll give you a demonstration.
הוו הנהו כלבי דהוו קא אכלי אינשי *havu hanhu kalvei de'havu ka
achli inshei*, there were certain evil dogs that would attack people. Okay,
שקל קלא *shakal kala*, he took a clump of earth, שדא בהו
*shada behu*, he threw it at those dogs. הוו קא אתו למכליה
*havu ka asu l'machleh*, they were going to come and attack him.
אמר אלהא דמאיר ענני *amar elaha de'Meir aneni*, God of Meir save
me. This is what... Rabbi Meir said. שבקוה, so they let him
alone, okay. So therefore he said, "Oh, I see that that works."
ויהיב ליה, veyahiv lei, so he gave it to him, he gave
him the bag of דינרי and then he saved the sister. לסוף
אשתמע מילתא בי מלכא, lesof ishtama milta be malka, eventually this was
heard in the by the, you know, in the house of the
king, you know, by the government. אתיוה אסקוה לזקיפה, atiyuh askuh lezekifa,
so they took him and they were going to execute him, not
Meir, the Roman officer that let her go.
Crucified him? Oh, crucified.
Right, probably, yikes. Rashi says hang him, you're right, it could be
crucified. אמר, and he said, אלהא דמאיר ענני, God of Meir save
me. אחתוה, achatuha, so they how they it was he couldn't be
hanged or he couldn't be crucified, something happened. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
fill in the details, but saying that saved him, prevented him from
being executed. Okay,
they tried and his neck was like iron and couldn't cut his
neck off. I don't know, whatever it was. Exactly like a מדרש
Midrash of משה. Moshe. Exactly. So אמרו ליה, amru lei, מאי האי?
mai hai? How did what
tell us the story? How did this work to save you from
execution? So אמר להו, amar lehu, הכי הוה מעשה, hachi hava maaseh,
he told them the whole story. אתו חקקו לדמותיה דרבי מאיר אפיתחא
דרומי, atu chakaku lidmutei deRabbi Meir apitcha deRomi, they went and they
engraved Rabbi Meir's face, they must have had one of those sketch
artists, okay, yeah,
his chin was a little more like this, they got a whole
sketch of him, they did a most wanted poster.
They put they they carved in the name, the face of Rabbi
Meir by the door, by the opening gates of Rome. אמרי, amri,
and they said, כל דחזי לפרצופא הדין, kol dechazi lepartzufa hadin, anybody
who sees somebody who looks like this, לייתיה לייתיה, leyatyei leyatyei, bring
him to us. Okay, he was like one of the most wanted,
okay, wanted dead or alive, Rabbi Meir. יומא חד חזיוה, yoma chad
chazyuh, one day they saw him, I don't know what Rabbi Meir
was doing in Rome, but one day they saw Rabbi Meir. Or
maybe they saw him outside of Rome, but by then knew his
picture, right, maybe there was a price on his head. רהטו בתריה,
rahatu batrei, they ran after him. רהט קמייהו, rahat kamaihu, he ran
away from them. על לבי זונות, al lvei zonot, he went into
the house of prostitution to save himself from them, because they figured
oh Rabbi Meir would never go into a house of prostitution. איכא
דאמרי, ika deamri, בשולי עובדי כוכבים חזא, bishulei ovdei kochavim chaza,
others say that, no, what happened was the way he faked it
was that there was a pot there of non-kosher food or of
food just cooked by non-Jews. טמש בהא, tamash beha, he dipped his
finger, he dipped one finger into the pot, ומתק בהא, umetack beha,
and he licked his other finger. So people saw it, thought that
he was licking the finger that was dipped in the pot.
See here he's being practical.
Exactly, that's the whole point. This is how you deal with the
Romans. You don't go and be, you know, make a big public
statement, you know, you make a side deal, you figure out how
you, you know, how you smuggle some, you know, Jews out of,
you know, out of Europe while the not, you know, whatever, you
figure out the ways to accommodate. When necessary, of course, but you
do it in a smart way.
There's a story about this pot or the fish or whatever and
then you have to, he teaches תורה Torah because, you know, yeah,
although I think that that's a little bit different because, well, we'll
get to, is that story coming up? But anyway, but that's just,
but there's a question about, well, that's a good question, but it
certainly that story wasn't in public. I don't think that story was
in public. Anyway, but that's a good question, we'll have to look
at that מדרש, Midrash, okay? Okay, איכא דאמרי, ika deamri, okay, איכא
דאמרי, ika deamri, אתא אליהו, ata Eliyahu,
a third version is Eliyahu came, אידמי להו כזונה, idmi lehu ke
zona, and he looked like a prostitute. כרכתיה, kerachtei, and he wrapped
himself around Rabbi Meir.
אמרי, amri, חס ושלום, chas veshalom, the Romans said, "God forbid, God
forbid this should be Rabbi Meir. אי רבי מאיר הוה לא הוה
עביד הכי, ei Rabbi Meir hava lo hava avid hachi, if this
was Rabbi Meir, he wouldn't act this way." קם ערק, kam arak,
so
finally, so Rabbi Meir got saved that one time, but Rabbi Meir
again, being very practical, realized that this was not going to mean
that he was always going to be saved. So he got up
and אתא לבבל, ata leBavel, he ran away to בבל. Bavel. So
I bet you didn't know that, that Rabbi Meir actually took refuge
in בבל. Bavel. איכא דאמרי מהאי מעשה, ika deamri mehai maaseh, some
say it was this story, ואיכא דאמרי ממעשה דברוריא, veika deamri mimaaseh
deBeruriah, and some say it was another story with Beruriah, which actually
was also like a, a terrible story that Beruriah was sort of
mocking the statement of the rabbis that
נשים דעתן קלות, nashim daatan kalot, and Rabbi Meir wanted to prove
her wrong and hired somebody to seduce her, and
whatever, it was a terrible story.
Okay, where is the story?
Rashi quotes קידושין. Kiddushin. All right. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now,
okay, so that is the end of those fascinating גמרות Gemaras about
the about these rabbis being executed, right, and on the one hand,
sort of the threat of the larger world as we see right
here: prostitution, the power of the government, right, these are the threats.
Before we had מינות, minut, heresy, that wasn't so much a dominant
point right here, okay. And the way you keep on the straight
and narrow is תורה, Torah, but you got to be practical. You
got to figure out how you're going to accommodate, right? Okay, so
now, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, now we get back to this issue
because we had mentioned stadium, and don't, don't build the stadium because
it's a place of violence, okay. And now we're going to talk
about some of the issues around the stadium, not just about violence,
but another issue which also ties into this again theme of what
are the real threats of the larger world. So they're very nicely
intertwined גמרות Gemaras here. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, ההולך לאצטדינין, haholech leitzitadinin,
one who goes to the stadium, ולכרקום, ulcharkom, and to... A כרקום
charkum which is basically when a—no, circus we're going to get to.
כרקום charkum is fortified camp. Right, it's—right, it's when people are basically
besieging a city. So if you imagine, you know, if you lay
a siege against a city, it's a lot of sitting and waiting,
okay? So you go there and then, you know, people are basically—they're
like, I don't know, they're having—they're, you know, they're like, they're having
a grand old time waiting for the city to fall, right, they
just have a lot of free time on their hands, okay? וראה
שם vera sham and you see there people doing like all of
these interesting types
of of like activity. את הנחשים ואת החברים et hanachashim ve'et hachavarim
you see like
the magicians and the snake charmers. בוקין מוקין מולין לולין בלורין סלגורין
bukin mukin mulin lulin belurin selgurin all these interesting things. Basically they
were like mimes and jugglers and all whatever I mean.
It was like a fair.
Yeah, exactly, a fair. That's a good point, like—right, exactly. And you
see all this fun stuff and you go there. What's the big
deal? I'm just having myself a good time. הרי זה מושב לצים.
harei zeh moshav leitzim. That is a—that is a place where the
mockers dwell. I mean, לצים leitzim is a good question what that
means, right? Does it mean frivolous spending of time? It sort of—Soncino
translates it as scornful, but scornful seems to not appropriate. I mean,
like, mocking.
In modern Hebrew it's a clown.
Clowns, right, clowns, like a joker, a mocker, you never take anything
seriously, everything is a joke, etc. Okay, so big deal. ועליהם הכתוב
אומר ve'aleihem hakatuv omeir אשרי האיש אשר לא הלך בעצת רשעים ובדרך
חטאים לא עמד ובמושב לצים לא ישב. ashrei ha'ish asher lo halach
ba'atzat resha'im uv'derech chata'im lo amad uv'moshav leitzim lo yashav. Praised is
the man that does not go in the way of the wicked
and does not sit with the jesters and the mockers and so
on. כי אם בתורת השם חפצו ki im b'torat Hashem cheftzo because
his real—his desire is in Torah. So here talking about something that
obviously is not as bad as like the sexual seductions and all
those other things, but is also what removes somebody from Torah. You
know, TV, your iPad, you know, Netflix, etc. Okay. כי אם בתורת
השם חפצו. ki im b'torat Hashem cheftzo. These are the things that
are, you know, not seen as—as evil, but they're seen as things
that ultimately eat away at what a real פרום frum life and
a commitment to תורה Torah is supposed to be. Okay. כי אם
בתורת השם חפצו. ki im b'torat Hashem cheftzo. הלמדת שדברים הללו מביאים
את האדם לידי ביטול תורה. halamadeta shed'varim halalu mevi'im et ha'adam lidei
bittul Torah. It's going to lead you away from תורה. Torah. Don't
say what's the big deal. You know, obviously it leads you away
from תורה Torah the five minute—the, you know, the time you're there,
but it leads you away from a—not just then. It has broader
implications. It leads you away from a life of immersion and intensity
in תורה. Torah. Okay. ורמינהי. veraminei. I'll ask you on this.
הולכין לאצטדינין מותר. holchin l'itztadinin mutar. We have a תוספתא Tosefta that
says that it's permissible to go to the stadia. מפני שצוח ומציל
mipnei shetzovei'ach umatzil because you can cry out and save somebody, meaning
when they, you know, when they have the gladiator games, if the
people, you know, do the thumbs up, then the guy gets saved.
So you can save a life. Okay. ולכרקום מותר. ul'charkum mutar. It's
permitted to go to this besiegement. מפני ישוב מדינה mipnei yishuv medinah
because, you know, maybe you'll be able to actually accomplish some political
aims, you know, you'll be able to—to get friendly with people in
power. רשי Rashi says maybe you'll be able to, you know, get
enough friendly with some of the army there that you'll be able
to influence how they—how they treat the people once they conquer it,
the city. ובלבד שלא יתחשב עמהם. u'vilvad shelo yitchasheiv imahem. But don't
sort of become one of them. Like, you know, you can get
close to them to try to have a position of influence, this
is again like be careful with the רשות, rashut, you know, but
don't go ahead and like be, you know, part—actual, you know, a
member. Okay. Be one—don't be one of them. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara says ואם נתחשב עמהם אסור. ve'im nitchasheiv imahem assur. And if
you do, then that's forbidden. You know, because you have to keep
your distance. Anyway. קשיא אצטדינין אאצטדינין קשיא כרקום אכרקום. kashya itztadinin a'itztadinin
kashya charkum a'charkum. There's a contradiction about both of these things, about
the stadia and about this besiegement, this camp of—of besiegement. בשלמא כרקום
אכרקום לא קשיא כאן במתחשב עמהם כאן בשאינו מתחשב עמהם. bishlama charkum
a'charkum lo kashya kan b'mitchasheiv imahem kan b'she'eino mitchasheiv imahem. We have
a way. When it said you can't go to be part of
this camp of besiegement, that's if you're really like going to be
unified with them and be one with them as opposed to if
you're going to like, you know, just try to influence them. Of
course, the funny thing is is that—is that it sounded like the—I
would have said the difference was what's your intent. Are you going
there because you want to see the—the jugglers and the dancers and
the mimes? That's forbidden. Are you going there because you want to
have some, you know, very good pragmatic purpose and you're trying to
influence them politically? That's a different story. Anyway, okay, that's number one.
But אלא אצטדינין אאצטדינין קשיא. ela itztadinin a'itztadinin kashya. How about the
stadia? Right, you know, if you're going there to save a life,
that should always be מותר. mutar. So the גמרא Gemara says תנאי
היא. tanna'ei hi. It's a dispute of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא אין הולכין
לאצטדינין מפני מושב לצים. detanya ein holchin l'itztadinin mipnei moshav leitzim. The
first position says you don't go there because it's a place of
mocking and jesting and whatever frivolity. Okay. רבי נתן מתיר. Rabbi Natan
matir. רבי נתן Rabbi Natan allows it מפני שני דברים mipnei shnei
devarim for two reasons. אחד מפני שצוח ומציל. echad mipnei shetzovei'ach umatzil.
One because you cry out and you can save a life. ואחד
מפני שמעיד עדות אשה להשיאה. ve'echad mipnei shemei'id eidut isha l'hasi'ah. And
the other is because you can also testify that if somebody does
get killed you can testify to and that his wife can get
remarried that you saw him killed. So the question is like really—so
why would the רבנן Rabbanan disagree? Like, these are really important purposes,
right? So I think that you could explain the רבנן Rabbanan would
disagree for two reasons. Number one is what's the real reason you're
going? You know... You're really going because you want to have a
good time, but you sort of rationalize it and oh, you know,
I'm going to go and you know what? I'll bring him to
my son's up thing, and if I see somebody get killed I'll
be able, but the real reason you're going is to have a
good time. So the rabbis sort of say like, no, give us
a break, we know what the real reason is that you're going
and so. Of course רבי יוסי Rabi Yose would say, what do
I care? If at the end of the day your presence there
can conduce some good, then it should be okay. You know, but
anyway, so that's one way of understanding. The other way is the
rabbis, you know, presumably right, if somebody is really going purely for
the purpose of saving the lives and testifying, I can't imagine that
the rabbis would be against it, but they see מושב לצים moshav
leitzim so horrific that we're not going to let somebody who's going
with this pure purpose. But I think the rabbis' point is give
us a break, it's not really why the person is going. Okay,
anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. We
taught. אין הולכין לטרטיאות ולקרקסיאות. Ein holchin le-tertiyot u-le-kirkasiyot. You don't go
to theaters and to circuses. מפני שמזבלין שם זיבול לעבודת כוכבים Mipnei
she-mezavlin sham zivul la-avodat kochavim because they do זיבול zivul for עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabi Meir. Now what's זיבול?
zivul? So רש"י Rashi says it means they do gatherings for עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. But תוספות Tosafot I think correctly says that this
is a classic way in which the rabbis, I told you before,
there's a great word, dysphemism, it's as opposed to euphemism, where they
take a word that is relating to another religion and they make
a slight change so it says, so it's derogatory. So תוספות Tosafot
says the real point they're saying is מזבחים שם זיבוח לעבודת כוכבים.
mizavchim sham zivuach la-avodat kochavim. They make sacrifices to עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. But when you change the ח chet to a ל, lamed,
זיבול, zivul, it means dung. Okay, they, you know, so they gather
up dung for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, which is a way of
saying they make sacrifices. Okay, like I told you, like you have
in זבול. zevul. Well no, that's what רש"י Rashi says. Okay, from
זבל zevel is what תוספות Tosafot says. The, in the time of
the ראשונים rishonim when they talked about the houses of prayer, they
called them בית תפלה, beit tifla, not בית תפילה. beit tefila. A
house of nonsense. Anyway, דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabi Meir. וחכמים אומרים
ve-chachamim omrim and the sages say, מקום שמזבלין אסור. makom she-mezavlin asur.
No, if it's a place where they do sacrifices it's forbidden. מפני
חשד עבודת כוכבים mipnei chashad avodat kochavim because it'll look like you're
participating in עבודה זרה. avoda zara. ומקום שאין מזבלין שם אסור u-makom
she-ein mezavlin sham asur and
that's why that's forbidden, and when they don't do sacrifices it's also
forbidden מפני מושב לצים. mipnei moshav leitzim. Because of מושב לצים. moshav
leitzim. So the גמרא says, so who cares? It's אסור asur for
one reason or another. Why do you, why are you making this
distinction? So the גמרא says מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? Who cares what
reason it's אסור? asur? Either way, theaters and circuses are אסור. asur.
So אמר רבי חנינא מסורא, amar Rabi Chanina mi-Sura, נשא ונתן איכא
בינייהו. nasa ve-natana ikka beinaihu. The difference is if you do business
when you're there. Okay, if it's about עבודה זרה, avoda zara, then
any proceeds from that business you have to get rid, destroy, right?
We learned that before. But if it's not about עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, just about מושב לצים moshav leitzim and a waste of time,
we're not going to fine you to get rid of the proceeds.
Okay, so one more דרשה drasha here about this מושב לצים. moshav
leitzim. דרש שמעון בן פזי. Darsh Shimon ben Pazi. מאי דכתיב? mai
de-chtiv? What's meant by the verse: אשרי האיש אשר לא הלך בעצת
רשעים ובדרך חטאים לא עמד ובמושב לצים לא ישב? Ashrei ha-ish asher
lo halach ba-atzat resha'im u-ve-derech chata'im lo amad u-ve-moshav leitzim lo yashav?
כי מאחר שלא הלך, Ki mei-achar she-lo halach, if the guy didn't
go in the way of the wicked, היכן עמד? heichan amad? How
does he ever be there long enough to stand? Stand means you're
not just you're going towards them but you're standing with them. ומאחר
שלא עמד, U-mei-achar she-lo amad, and if he didn't stand with them,
היכן ישב? heichan yashav? How does he, how does he sit? Because
it says, praised is the man who didn't go in the way
of the wicked and didn't stand, you know, with the sinners and
didn't sit with the לצים. leitzim. So if you didn't do the
first one, you're not going to do the later ones.
ומאחר שלא ישב היכן לץ? U-mei-achar she-lo yashav heichan lutz? Then how
does it lead to him being a לץ? leitz? He never got
to that stage. אלא לומר לך, Ella lomar lach, this to tell
you, no, exactly, if you stop at the beginning, it won't go
on with the progression. But if you don't stop in the beginning,
this is going to be the progression. לומר לך שאם הלך, lomar
lach she-im halach, if you start just, I'm just going, you know,
like it says like that echoing the phrase of הלך לטרטיאות ולקרקסיאות.
halach le-tertiyot u-le-kirkasiyot.
I'm just going to check it out, there's a fair going on,
I'm just going to walk by, it's fun, it's interesting. Okay, שאם
הלך, she-im halach, if you
go, where were we, שאם הלך סוף לעמוד, she-im halach sof la-amod,
you're not just going to walk by, you'll stay there, you'll spend
some time in the circus, in the fair. ואם עמד, ve-im amad,
and if you stand there, סוף לשב, sof lashev, oh, might as
well sit, spend an hour here. ואם ישב, ve-im yashav, and after
sitting there, סוף ללוץ, sof lalutz, then you'll become caught up in
all of that mockery and frivolity and you know, it leads to
basically also the other point here besides ביטול תורה bitul Torah is,
you know, it's a real question about do you have a sense
of like seriousness of purpose in your life? You know, your life
is a serious thing. I mean, you know, that people will sort
of say like, you know, you know, that's like an issue, you
know, in the contemporary culture with all I was, you know, saying,
you know, iPads and Facebook and Netflix and all that stuff, it's
like, you know, life is just about entertainment, right? Now, it's, you
know, it's like you just want to like
whittle away the time, entertain, things are trivial, okay, so that's part
of the לצים leitzim problem. The לץ leitz is the exact opposite
of like a seriousness of purpose, a seriousness of why I'm on
this earth and so on.
So it's an attitude which leads them to keep to the masses...
Right, exactly, to keep the masses occupied. But the point is to
get you caught up, it's not just a question of time, it's
a different way in which you relate to what your life is
all
about. and what you do with your time and how what your
time should be spent. Okay, so ואם עמד סופה לישב נמצא סופה
ללוץ. v'im amad sofa l'shaiv nimtza sofa l'lotz. ואם לץ, v'im latz,
and if you become a לץ, leitz, ולבסוף הכתוב אומר, v'labasof hakatuv
omer, אם חכמת חכמת לך, im hachamta hachamta lach, if you're wise
you'll be wise for yourself, ולצת לבדך תשא, v'latzta levadcha tisa, and
if you become a לץ, leitz, that'll be your own burden to
carry. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, כל המתלוצץ, kol hamitzlotzeitz, if
anybody who becomes a לץ, leitz, who's like a mocker, a jester,
whatever, you're like, you know, a frivolous, ייסורין באין עליו, yisurin ba'in
alav, you bad things will happen to you, שנאמר, shene'emar, ועתה אל
תתלוצצו, v'ata al tislotzatzu, do not become do not become scornful or
do not become a mocker, פן יחזקו מוסריכם, pen yechezkuh moseireichem, lest
your afflictions become strong. אמר להו רבא לרבנן, Amar lehu Rava l'rabanan,
רבא Rava said to the רבנן, rabanan, the rabbinical
students, במטותא, bimatusa, like, you know, at your leave, like do me
a favor guys, בעינא מינייכו דלא תתלוצצו, ba'ina mineichu d'lo tislotzatzu, don't
kid around, you know, don't be so frivolous. Like he's saying this
to rabbinical students, like maybe he walked into a שיעור shiur once
and they were all telling some joke. I mean you're also supposed
to tell a joke when you start a שיעור, shiur, but whatever,
they weren't just telling jokes, they were being totally frivolous. He said
look, do me a favor, that's really a bad מידה, midah, דלא
ליתו עלייכו ייסורין, d'lo leisu aleichu yisurin, and bad things will happen
to you. אמר רב קטינא, Amar Rav Katina, כל המתלוצץ מזונותיו מתמעטין,
kol hamitzlotzeitz mezonosav mitmatin, if you if you המתלוצץ, mitlotzeitz, if you
spend your time with these frivolities, you will have less food, meaning
you'll make less of an income, because you know, that's another thing,
if you have a seriousness of purpose you could be driven not
in תורה, Torah, you could be driven in business. You know, but
if you're spending all your time with entertainment and frivolity, you're not
going to be earning as much money. שנאמר משך ידו את לוצים,
shene'emar mashach yado es lotzim, God withdraws his hand from the לוצים,
lotzim, his hand that sustains the world. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
Amar Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish, כל המתלוצץ נופל בגיהנום, kol hamitzlotzeitz nofel
b'gehinnom, eventually they're going to lead you down to the path of
perdition. שנאמר, shene'emar, you like that word perdition, when's the last time
you heard somebody say that? שנאמר זד יהיר לץ שמו, shene'emar zeid
yahir leitz shemo, a haughty one,
you know, is like wicked and he is called a לץ. leitz.
עושה בעברת זדון, oseh b'evras zadon, he does in, you know, in
transgression or in wickedness his evil. ואין עברה אלא גיהנום, v'ein evrah
ela gehinnom, and עברה, evrah, anger, עברה, evrah, אלא גיהנום, ela gehinnom,
שנאמר יום עברה היום ההוא. shene'emar yom evrah hayom hahu. Fine. אמר
רבי אושעיה, Amar Rebbe Oshaya, כל המתיהר, kol hamisyaher, now since the
word also spoke about יהיר, yahir, haughty and arrogant, right, so we'll
say the same about arrogant, anybody who's arrogant
נופל בגיהנום, nofel b'gehinnom, שנאמר זד יהיר לץ שמו עושה בעברת זדון
ואין עברה אלא גיהנום שנאמר יום עברה היום ההוא. shene'emar zeid yahir
leitz shemo oseh b'evras zadon v'ein evrah ela gehinnom shene'emar yom evrah
hayom hahu. אמר רבי חנילאי בן חנילאי, Amar Rebbe Chanilai ben Chanilai,
interesting, father same name, כל המתלוצץ גורם כליה לעולם, kol hamitzlotzeitz goreim
kalyah l'olam, you bring destruction to the
world. שנאמר ועתה אל תתלוצצו פן יחזקו מוסריכם כי כלה ונחרצה שמעתי,
shene'emar v'ata al tislotzatzu pen yechezkuh moseireichem ki chalah v'necheratzah shamati, because
destruction I have heard and therefore destruction to the world. אמר רבי
אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, קשה היא שתחילתה ייסורין, kashah hi shetechilasah yisurin,
it begins with just personal affliction when you're a לץ, leitz, וסופה
כליה, v'sofah kalyah, and it ends with destruction. דרש רבי שמעון בן
פזי, Darash Rebbe Shimon ben Pazi, אשרי האיש, Ashrei ha'ish, so this
is a great end for we'll end here for today, he worked
this into the פסוק pasuk itself. אשרי האיש אשר לא הלך, Ashrei
ha'ish asher lo halach, you know, the end of the פסוק pasuk
is בעצת רשעים, ba'atzas resha'im, the path of the wicked. But he
said אשרי האיש אשר לא הלך לברקיטאות ולקרקסיאות, Ashrei ha'ish asher lo
halach l'varkita'os u'l'kirkasa'os, you know, he weaved it into the verse, praise
be the man who did not go to the theaters and the
circuses. של עובדי כוכבים. shel ovdei kochavim. ובדרך חטאים לא עמד, u'v'derech
chata'im lo amad, and didn't stand with the wicked, שלא עמד בקניגיון,
she'lo amad b'kangiyon, he didn't stand like with the קניגיון, kangiyon, some
type of like with wild animals, like a type of a sport.
Okay. ובמושב לצים לא ישב, u'v'moshav leitzim lo yashav, שלא ישב בתחבולות,
she'lo yashav b'tachbulos, and he did not sit in תחבולות, tachbulos, which
is also some type of a gathering of entertainment. שמא יאמר אדם
הואיל ולא הלכתי לברקיטאות וקרקסיאות ולא עמדתי בקניגיון אלך ואידרדם בשינה, shema
yomar adam ho'il v'lo halachti l'varkita'os v'kirkasa'os v'lo amadeti b'kangiyon eilech v'idardam
b'sheinah, okay fine, the rabbis told me I'm not supposed to go
and entertain myself, but you know, let me just sleep away my
day. תלמוד לומר ובתורתו יהגה יומם ולילה, Talmud lomar u'v'soraso yehegeh yomam
valailah, it's not enough to not do bad, you have to do
good. You have to invest your life in purposeful living and in
living a life of תורה, Torah, and in the end of course
the theme here that you keep to a path of תורה, Torah,
but you know, try to be a little smarter than רבי חנינא
בן תרדיון Rebbe Chanina ben Teradyon and try to know how to
accommodate the larger world in which you live, but ultimately it's your
commitment to a life of תורה Torah that is what the Jewish
life is all about and the goal to keep you on the
straight and narrow. Okay, so we will end with that.